A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, DNA, Series G FA342
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, DNA, Series G
1958-1968
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Abby Aldrich
Whitman, Ann
Ruebhausen, Oscar M.
Inter-American Development Commission
Rockefeller, Mary (Mary Todhunter Clark)
United States. Dept. of Health and Human Services
United States. International Development Advisory Board
Morrow, Hugh
United States. Office of Inter-American Affairs
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Rockefeller family
United States. Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs
United States. Dept. of State
United States. President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization
Hinman, George
United States. Dept. of State. Bureau of Western Hemisphere Affairs
FA342
31 Document Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 G
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for scholarly research. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted from scholarly access.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into three subseries: Subseries 1 - Notebooks Subseries 2 - Files for the 1968 Campaign Subseries 3 - Files for Other Campaigns and Issues
Scope and Contents note
Although the acronym DNA may have stood for Definitive News Analysis, no corroboration has been found in the written record. The staff of DNA were on Rockefeller's personal payroll.
There were two main divisions to DNA, a research group for Nelson Rockefeller. The Domestic Policy staff was overseen by Roswell B. Perkins, while the Foreign Policy Staff was led by Henry Kissinger. In later years, DNA was headed by Oscar M. Ruebhausen. The main function of the organization was to draft position papers and research reports on issues important to the Governor's pursuit of the Republican presidential nomination.
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of several members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. These files document official activities in the execution of their duties as members of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller which were never shown to him.
Related Archival Materials note
Researchers may want to review other materials that may relate to this series that can be found in Record Group 15, Series 17: Issue Books.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - George L. Hinman (FA346)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Art, Primitive; Agriculture -- Latin America; Brazil; Arts; Federal government -- United States; Government agencies; Agriculture; Education -- Latin America; Economic policy; Developing countries; Education; Economics; Business enterprises, Foreign; Business; Philanthropy -- United States; Civics; Civic improvement; Philanthropy; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Political campaigns -- United States; National security -- United States; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Social problems -- Latin America; State governments -- United States; United States; Venezuela; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Public health -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Latin America; International economic relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; International relations -- United States; International relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Museum of Primitive Art (New York, N.Y.); Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); International Basic Economy Corporation; American International Association for Economic and Social Development; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.); United Nations; Rockefeller Brothers Fund
- Notebooks, 1; 3.2 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  These notebooks (originally in large black binders that have been discarded) contain position papers, press releases, memoranda, and correspondence on issues during the 1968 Presidential campaign. Both foreign and domestic policy issues are represented here. This subseries contains opposition research on the 1968 Republican presidential nominee, Richard Nixon. There are also information on issue positions for other candidates in 1968, including Hubert Humphrey, Ronald Reagan, and Robert Kennedy.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. I) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Tab 1 Arms Control - background paper. Tab 2 "Building a Just World Order" - press release, May 1, 1968. Tab 3 Burns Letter - "My Concept of the Presidency," prepared for "Life" magazine [correspondence from NAR to James MacGregor Burns on article Burns is writing for the magazine]. Tab 4-6 China, Mainland - position paper; questions and answers; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP. Tab 7-9 Commitments, United States - press release, June 12, 1968; outline of press release, June 7, 1968; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP. Tab 10-12 Cuba - press release, August 2, 1958; draft statement on Cuba by Nancy Maginnes and Peter Rodman; background memo to Richard Aldrich from Stuart Morrison. Tab 13-20 Defense - recommended positions; questions and answers; Background papers.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. I) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Tab 21-25 Defense - recommended positions; questions and answers; Background papers. Tab 26-31 Eastern Europe - fact sheets; positions comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP, position papers; background papers; press releases, Czechoslovakia.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. II) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Tab 1-5 Economic Policy - press releases; draft statements; fact sheets. Tab 6-8 Foreign Aid - fact sheets; question and answers; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP. Tab 9-11 Germany - press release; fact sheets. Tab 12 Japan - fact sheets. Tab 13 [Robert] Kennedy Assassination - meeting notes with John Gardner, Caryl Haskins, Henry Kissinger. Tab 14-15 Latin America - press release, questions and answers; draft speech; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. II) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Tab 16-17 Latin America - press release, questions and answers; draft speech; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP. Tab 18-20 Middle East - fact sheets; questions and answers; draft speech; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP. Tab 21-24 National Science Policy - press release, draft speech; views of Richard Morse, July 11, 1968; background paper. Tab 25-29 National Security - press release; draft speech; background papers, position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. III) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Tab 1-5 Non-Proliferation Treaty - press release; draft speech; questions and answers; background paper; Kissinger memo to NAR, June 8, 1968. Tab 6-7 Pueblo - background paper; questions and answers. Tab 8-11 Republican Platform - "Where Are We Now in the Campaign," June 9, 1968; outline of suggestions for the Republican Platform, June 30, 1968; complete text of 1968 Republican Platform; press release, NAR acceptance of platform. Tab 12-13 Rensselaer Commencement - draft of address to Rensselaer Commencement, May 20, 1968; outline of remarks. Tab 14 Southeast Asia - fact sheets. Tab 15 United Nations - fact sheets; questions and answers; background papers; draft speeches; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP; press releases.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. III) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Tab 16-23 United Nations - fact sheets; questions and answers; background papers; draft speeches; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP; press releases. Tab 24-31 U.S.S.R. - fact sheets; questions and answers; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP; press releases.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, General (vol. IV) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Tab 1-11 Western Europe and NATO - fact sheets; questions and answers; position comparisons, NAR, Nixon, GOP; press releases; draft speech; background papers.
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Vietnam (vol. V) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Tab 1 Background Paper Tab 2-10 Speeches and Drafts
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Vietnam (vol. V) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Tab 11-21 Speeches and Drafts
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Vietnam (vol. VI) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Tab 1-7 Briefing Memos to NAR Tab 8-11 Memos from Advisors Tab 12-18 Questions and Answers
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Vietnam (vol. VI) (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Tab 19-20 Questions and Answers Tab 21 Press Conferences
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, News Conferences (vol. VII) (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Tab 1 Balance of Payments Tab 2-6 China Tab 7-9 Commitments, United States Tab 10 Defense Tab 11-12 Foreign Aid Tab 13 Foreign Policy Tab 14-15 France Tab 16 Gold Tab 17-19 Middle East Tab 20-22 Pueblo Tab 23 Secretary of State Tab 24 Southeast Asia Tab 25-26 Trade Tab 27-28 United Nations Tab 29 U.S.S.R. Tab 30 Summary of NAR Foreign Policy Positions Tab 31 Statements on Foreign Policy by NAR
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Meetings (vol. VIII) (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Tab 1-3 Africa Tab 4 Asia Tab 5 Cornell Group Tab 6 Communist Trends Tab 7-13 Defense and Science Tab 14 Latin America Tab 15 Middle East
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Meetings (vol. VIII) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Tab 16-18 Middle East Tab 19 Organizational Problems of Government Tab 20-21 United Nations Tab 22 Western Europe
  - Notebooks: Foreign Policy, Republican Convention (vol. IX) (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Tab 1 Committee Membership Tab 2 Rockefeller Draft of Foreign Policy Platform Tab 3 V.I.P. Speeches and Statements - speeches by Richard Nixon, George Romney, Ronald Reagan, John V. Lindsay, Dwight D. Eisenhower. Tab 4 Platform: GOP Drafts I and II Tab 5 Suggested Language for Foreign Policy Platform Tab 6 Vietnam Plank Tab 7 Other Planks Proposed - planks offered on Western Europe and NATO, Eastern Europe, Latin America, Foreign Aid, National Security, "Our Fighting Men in Vietnam." Tab 8 Complete Text of 1968 Republican Platform Tab 9 Rockefeller Statement Endorsing the Platform Tab 10 Article - "Rockefeller Coup Gave Platform a Dovish Tone," by John W. Finney, "New York Times," August 6, 1968. Tab 11 Molitor-Geilich Memoranda on Rockefeller-Reagan Difference Tab 12 I. F. Stone on Rockefeller - article from "I. F. Stone's Weekly" on Rockefeller's Record as a Hawk.
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Agriculture (vol. I) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Tab 1-8 General Tab 9-10 Food and Agriculture Act of 1965 Tab 11-12 Land Restoration Tab 13 Urban-Rural Balance Tab 14-15 Farm Income Stabilization Tab 16-17 National Farmers Organization (NFO)
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Cities (vol. II) (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Tab 1-9 General Tab 10-15 Urban Development Corporation (UDC) Tab 16-18 Housing Tab 19 "New Cities" - press release, July 22, 1968. Tab 20-22 Air and Water Pollution Tab 23 Mass Transportation Tab 24 Proposal for Community Development Tab 25-27 Urban Capital Development Tab 28 Urban Business Corps
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Civil Rights and Civil Disorders (vol. III) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Tab 1-8 General Tab 9 Civil Rights Law Enforcement Tab 10-12 "Poor People's Campaign" Tab 13-17 Civil Disorder Tab 18 Federal Department of Human Rights
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Crime (vol. IV) (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Tab 1-8 General Tab 9 Gun Control - wire to Price Daniels, June 14, 1968. Tab 10-13 Gun Control - press releases. Tab 14-19 Gun Control - materials on Nixon position. Tab 20-21 Gun Control - materials on Federal Legislation. Tab 22-27 Gun Control - background materials.
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Crime, continued (vol. V) (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Tab 1 Omnibus Crime Bill - Michigan Q&A. Tab 2-6 Omnibus Crime Bill - Background Materials. Tab 7-10 Omnibus Crime Bill - Nixon and Title II. Tab 11 Organized Crime - press release. Tab 12-13 Organized Crime - Electronic surveillance. Tab 14-16 Narcotic Addiction Tab 17-19 Civil Disorders Tab 20-23 Administration of Justice Tab 24 Juvenile Delinquency Tab 25 Rehabilitation
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Economy (vol. VI) (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Tab 1-7 General Tab 8 Balance of Payments Tab 9-15 Inflation Tab 16-18 Post-Vietnam Economic Policy Tab 19-23 Small Business Tab 24 "Barron's" Editorial Refutation
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Education (vol. VII) (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Tab 1-7 General
  - Notebooks: Domestic Policy, Education (vol. VII) (Box 4, Folder 23)